welcome to meditating with john vervicky
i'm a cognitive psychologist and
cognitive scientist at the university of
toronto
i teach and scientifically study on
topics like mindfulness
and related topics like insight
flow mystical experience transformative
experience higher states of
consciousness
the cultivation of wisdom the aspiration
towards
enlightenment and virtue
i've also been practicing but past the
meditation for
29 years as well as metacontemplation
and tai chi tai chi chuan
i've been practicing them for 29 years
like as an ecology of practices
mutually supporting constraining and
affording each other
in addition i've been teaching them
close to 20 years
in various professional settings
sometimes at the university of toronto
the multi-faith center
and various martial arts dojos
alternative health centers
so a lot of different venues a lot of
different teaching experiences
welcome this is a progressive course
uh up until now every monday has been a
dharma day
in which we have been meeting and i will
teach a practice or principle
that builds on previous practices and
principles
if you want to catch up there's the
links in the description
to this video of previous lessons we're
not going to start slowing down the pace
at which i start teaching new material
to give people a chance to catch up
and also to give people who have been
doing the course
a chance to review and refresh and renew
next monday i'm going to start an
advanced technique
and it's going to be called it is called
lectio divina
which is means divine reading for those
of you who want to do this more advanced
technique it's a way of
learning to read that is conducive and
supportive
of the cultivation of wisdom the
cultivation of mindfulness etc
if you can i'm not requiring anything uh
if you can find a text
that you find sacred in some sense
that would be good i'm going to use
and i if you can i recommend trying to
get a text
that is sacred poetry here's one by
stephen mitchell's particularly good
anthologies are excellent
but you may have a text by roomie or
perhaps
you know by you know saint john the
cross
something that is poetry and sacred to
you
and then also something perhaps that's
prose that you can
it's good to have a combination sacred
prose
uh maybe it's some uh philosoph a
philosopher you particularly like
uh maybe it's uh important texts like
the bhagavad gita or the taute
maybe it's the bible try and find
something
you can find at least one that's great
if you can find an example of
both uh poetry and prose you'll be able
to practice with
uh extensively uh that's good so i'll be
taking you through
how to do uh lucio divina this is a way
remember the buddha the dharma this is a
way of
doing dharma you're not just learning
and consuming information
you're reading not for information
you're reading for transformation
and so that's what i'm going to be
teaching you uh with lexia
there's some things you can do to help
me please please like this video stream
because it will raise
its profile and presence for the youtube
algorithm and that will help me to reach
more people with this course
and with this community i'm very very
grateful
and impressed by the community that's
growing around uh
this course the sangha is amazing um the
questions
the participation and the involvement
and the commitment is truly truly
honorable and should be honored which is
what i'm doing right now
at the end of every lesson so every
other monday will be a dharma day
next monday's lecture demina every day
we sit together monday through friday
at the end of every sit there's q a
please limit the q a's during those
times to
questions about the ecology practices
the course that i'm teaching
if you have more general questions
perhaps about how this fits into the
broader framework of buddhism or how
compares to stoicism
what it has to do say about what this
has to do with cultivation of wisdom
or responding to the meeting crisis then
please
bring those general questions to a live
q a
we have every third friday of
the month at 3 00 pm eastern time live
streamed
on youtube i think that's it for now
i think that's everything we could do to
begin so
uh please set your phones on do not
disturb
please get your basic posture ready and
then we will begin
when i say begin beginning
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness and
cognition
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
all right we have some time for some
questions we can
typically go a little bit longer on
mondays and wednesday
a little bit longer fridays at the end
sharply on tuesdays and thursdays
gabriel rubenstein asks in the past i
find counting my thoughts difficult but
i can
recall the thoughtlessness after
handling a distraction and meditate on
that can i skip the counting and
train method any thanks uh yes i mean if
you can
get to that space because you're getting
a very salient
felt sense of the thoughtlessness after
distraction
and then you can just find that as the
focus
of deeper vipassana yes by all means
all of these things are wraths you use
them to get to a place
once you can reliably get there without
needing the scaffolding or the inner
coaching or the end of talking
you let it go and you just directly do
the practice so if you find
that you can reliably right without
without
needing to use you know the the counting
and the train method
if you can reliably sense your way
remembering
that felt sense of what it's like to be
thoughtless i'm in
in the sense you're using it right and
then meditate into that space
do it by all means by all means that's a
general principle
all right because of all of these things
i'm teaching you
eventually you like like i said you
you'll just be able to center and root
right and then you'll learn new dharma
and you might learn
a new practice that re-scaffolds you in
a way you haven't developed yet then you
practice that for a while this is a very
organic living thing it evolves it
evolves
uh i think it's dimitar uh due to a
depressive mood
or a variety of factors i'm very often
drowsy even though i'm very physically
active
besides meditating as much as possible
during my peak energy levels
and trying to address the issues
generally do you have any suggestions on
making my mindfulness
practice more robust against this yes so
one of the things i am going to do
um in the advanced techniques that teach
you some moving minds honest practices
uh some chica i'll teach you some basic
chi khan
um some each one some janjung a little
bit of tai chi
give you a bunch of moving things you
can do that will help
uh in order to help you
get um a more energetic state be the
platform
um in which you are cultivating
mindfulness uh that will be coming
shortly
um and i hope that will help
um i don't know about your particular
physiology and you mentioned depression
there's
there you might be under treatment
so give that absolute priority
but you know it's it's part of the
tradition also for people who are having
a kind of drowsiness
uh to also drink some green tea uh about
you know 15-20 minutes before
uh meditating uh to try and help um
you can't rely on that you know ongoing
but maybe that'll
help get you to learn a different
metabolic state
and hopefully with the moving
mindfulness that will help as well
again when i recommend anything like
that i do that
with utmost caution and hesitation i
don't know your particular physiology i
don't know your your psychological state
i don't know what your therapeutic
situation
is i don't know your medical history
both physical
or uh on mental health issues
so take that all into consideration and
consult whoever you need to consult
but you know maybe taking the green tea
will help you
and definitely the moving mindfulness
practices i'm going to teach shortly
will be obeyed to you andrew castley
mind if i ask what your thoughts on
thought forms are
for example buddha projecting infinite
versions himself into the dimensions
um i don't know
a lot about
the particular metaphysics you what i
mean is i'm ignorant about what the
particular metaphysics is
you're invoking here uh uh you might be
uh referring to a thought what's called
a thought only form
uh of buddhism or maybe an aspect of
vajrayana tibetan buddhism you might be
talking about the relationship between
relative and absolute
reality i don't know which one you're
referring to so it's a difficult
question to answer it might be
if you re-ask your question perhaps i
feel to be premature
it gave me a little bit more context in
which you're asking that question
because
it's right now as i've tried to indicate
it's a big use to me where you're coming
from
and i don't know which question i'm
supposed to be answering uh so if you
could
uh try that again i'd be happy to give
it a better shot
when i get a better sense of where
you're coming from
today i didn't give myself mental
instructions i was peaceful no monkey
mind i started to feel maybe i'm doing
it wrong
should i continue with or without or
alternate the mental instructions
um as i've said um again i'm not inside
your head and this is you know this is
it just requires you know tremendous
self-honesty on all of our parts
if you can do the practice without
having to talk to yourself
and do the practice without having to
talk to yourself um
but i do recommend right if you just sit
and your mind goes
sort of blank no monkey mind that's very
peaceful uh
but you might not be getting yourself
into the deepest possible state
remember the buddha is very very many
traditions in fact one against us
about just seeking a kind of peaceful
contentedness
this is not a vacation from stress it is
an education for resiliency and
transformation
so if you're making sure you have the
core if you can do the core four without
having to talk to yourself
and if you can bring in the inquiring
mindfulness and
pursue it an ever deepening reciprocal
opening in your practice
if you can do all of that without
instruction that's fine but if you're
just getting into a kind of static
you know unmoving unexploring peaceful
contemptedness
that's actually not conducive to
transformation
it's conducive for restoration
but if you want to actually
afford what this practice can most
deeply offer you
you need to make sure that the
transformative principles are in
practice
so i hope that answers your question uh
now bella
my student uh good to see you um
when stating the five promises i add and
with love after each one and i find that
it deepens my commitment to myself
uh this is like reciprocal opening i do
the same
i actually do the same um and i
you know i often say you know i could do
it you know mindfully
carefully in the sense of both taking
care and you know caring about
and lovingly um as a way and of trying
to remember
i'm doing this remembering the being
mode
in the cultivation of wisdom so i think
that's an excellent uh thing to do
you know again i don't want to lay too
much on people
and so just give the basic thing of
mindfully
but if there are things that
spontaneously come up that
deepen your commitment deep in your
sense of reciprocal opening
deepening your ability to sati remember
the being will
deepen your aspiration towards the
cultivation of wisdom
then add them but don't overburden the
promises either
either so you're trying to get you know
an optimal grip on them just the right
amount
uh so that it's always transformative
but not too much
so that you're merely enduring saying
all the things that you're trying to say
calder morgan ferguson what could be the
cause of feeling of frustration during
meditation or what are strategies to
manage this
um that's a difficult question uh it
could be that you
uh there's many different possibilities
here and again i don't know you
personally could be
one of these one is uh we're carrying
around sort of a background frustration
that we're sort of
keeping at the fringes of our awareness
or suppressing it
uh marginalizing it and when we when we
sort of shut off
what is normally focal that can come
into awareness
um then of course what you want to do is
you want to do the five factors on the
frustration
you want to and you also want to direct
meta towards it
you want to try and go from being into a
confrontational relationship
to it where you're facing it whether
where we're
facing now means giving it a face
allowing it
uh to speak to you what is it you need
to be addressing what is it you need to
be learning
and then you may want to pay attention
to uh becoming
trying to notice moments in your life
where you're experiencing frustration
and trying to bring the mindfulness
practices uh to that that might be
one reason another reason might be
there's something in you that's fighting
it's a form of resistance that's
actually fighting
um doing the meditation itself there's a
transformation
uh so you you need to maybe
slow down your effort a little bit um
you need to again do the same thing try
to do the five factors
uh and crying mindfulness on the
frustration where is it in your body and
all that all that stuff
i've taught you and also again direct
meta towards it try to open it up
there's something there that's trying to
slow you down
caution you you also want to make sure
you're doing the things that help keep
your motivation
strong you know the buddha the dharma
the sangha
try to remember moments where the
opposite where you're really getting in
sync you're really
cutting deeply through any illusion
you're seeing into the depths of things
you're resonating with the
moments where you're where the buddha is
present to you celebrate them remember
them
dharma you know reading more i'm going
to teach you the lectio divina how to
read more deeply in a transformative
manner
learn more be transform work you know
the only way we can be informed by
what's transcendent
is how it transforms us that's the only
way we get informed by it we have to
first be transformed
uh towards it so that's uh
what you want to do and then saying it
keep meeting here talk to other people
maybe
you know get involved with the ch chat
in uh
saying ask other people um if they're
you know experiencing any frustration
get some feedback
get a sense of what's going on um and so
that's what i would recommend as
probably
what i think are probably two of the
most probable uh sources of the
frustration and how you could address
them you could also have a mixture of
both
so see if that helps yes
if there is an issue to meditate just uh
after running i think i'm only getting
part of that question
all i'm getting is if there is any issue
to meditating just oh i'm sorry i
misread it
um i uh uh i don't think so
um right after running is probably good
as long as you know your heart isn't
pounding and you're not breathing
heavily
you've done enough of a warm down uh but
yeah going actually that's very good
to meditate right after running because
you've got your oxygenated you've
probably got
some cognitive flexibility going uh a
high degree of brain activation the
cerebellum
has been activated the cerebellum uh
cortex loop um i
i think that would actually be excellent
as long as i said you're not just
feeling your heart pounding
or you've you've done a proper warm down
uh mark lefebvre hi mark mark is uh and
you know his participation in the sangha
his support of it
his affordance of it his good spirited
commitment to it is much appreciated
um i'm getting just better elucidation
on the difference between flow
and focus so
the they are deeply interpenetrating um
and um flow is very much about
opening up that field of introspective
awareness
uh where its focus is
right the degree to which you're
following the focal uh area of your
breath remember field and focus
and what's being maintained there is
more about the continuity
so flow is more about sort of trying to
fill the whole of the body with the
whole of the mind
and then uh focus is more about trying
to get a sense of
momentum to this but but as you're
rightly noting
that has an aspect of flow to it because
when you get into flow
it helps you be more absorbed it makes
it more self-organizing which is
precisely why i teach you
flow but before i teach you a focus um
they you should find that there's a
continuum between them
they're not totally identical uh where
you know
i would say that uh flow is more sort of
about the embodiment
of what you do of the breath and then
focus is more about the enactment how
one moment
of mindfulness is leading to the next
but there is it can
definitely a continuum between them
matthew mccready i sometimes find myself
rooting centering or finding my flow in
my normal life
is this like meditating before sleep and
should it only be done when i'm sitting
no it's not like meditating before do
more of that matthew
encourage that that's that's celebrating
your buddha
if you find yourself centering rooting
and finding your flow throughout your
normal life
that is exactly what you want that
spontaneous transfer that's your buddha
coming into existence nurture that
celebrate that that is amazing that is
great
that is good ben gao
i am confused about matter towards
myself is wanting to be secure
or esteemed having myself is what is
wanting to be more able and effective
having myself what is reciprocal opening
towards oneself
reciprocal opening towards oneself is
precisely not to have oneself
um and it's not about what you want for
yourself
it's about what you have not seen or
realized about yourself
it's about opening it's like when you
learn when you're falling in love with
somebody
and you see what you haven't seen about
them before it's not what you
want from them if you just want from
somebody else you're not actually loving
them
it's what you're what you're seeing what
you're realizing
in a resonant fashion about them that
you haven't realized or seen before
that's what you're after when you're
doing meta towards yourself
you're trying to take an open stance
towards it because the idea is when we
genuinely
there's a kind of goodness that's not
the goodness of affection it's the
goodness of
genuine realization and so we're trying
the the opening
right the the open affect where you're
sort of
may i be happy and healthy remember
that's not the goal you're not you're
not
wanting that for yourself you're trying
to put yourself into an open
positive attitude because that
facilitates reciprocal opening it is a
method it's not a goal
the goal is is to try and realize
what you have not seen about yourself
before open up
that's why you know the inquiring
mindfulness is also relevant to meta
in a particular way that sense of
opening up unlocking your
your identity letting it be other than
how you have always had it
or want to have it that's exactly what
you're trying to do
in meta uh nishargo
i doubted what unconscious drives
motivated me to meditate and i'm not
sure why i continue to practice it
anymore should i continue meditating
without a good reason
um so that's a good question and what
typically happens
when we're aspiring which means to go
through transformation and become
someone different be a different person
with different perspectives
and a different identity that's what it
is when you want to go from being
foolish
to wise or cowardly to courageous
right these are aspirational your
reasons for doing it
will change why you started
meditating is not why you will continue
meditating
keep practicing and let the re a new
reason for why you're meditating emerge
out of the practice
not just the practice in the sitting but
your practice in your life
let that let the new because that new
reason is
actually you moving to a new perspective
a new way of being
if you keep trying to start with your
original motive you will stay in the
world and the original
place you were in you will not actually
afford aspiration
julianne weinstein question about
overconsumption of spiritual talks and
teachings online seems to be something i
do a lot hours of listening to
enlightened folks but very little time
spent practicing any advice
yes um so um
you're noticing uh something that we all
fall prey to
uh it's what's the what's the proverb
i forget what it is it's something like
i buy the i i buy the book and confuse
it with
reading the book right um so
getting consuming beliefs and statements
from people
um is very much a having mode thing
and we all fall prey to this i'm not
trying to be accusative i'm trying to be
helpful to you
and this is why i often say to people
don't tell me what you believe
tell me what you practice because it's
only in the practice that we'll get the
transformation
and only in the transformation will we
become conformed
and thereby informed about what
transcends us because
if we're trying to grow we have to come
into relation to what transcends us
as we are now there is no
other way and so if you're constantly
assimilating just constantly taking it
in
right gathering and you're actually not
accommodating
you're not actually practicing coming
into a process of transformation
and so very often this kind of modal
confusion
um it has to do with the fact
that we are attracted if there's
something
calling us we feel called to the
transformation but there's some
underlying anxiety about actually
pursuing the transformation
so we substitute it's in cognitive
science it's called satisficing we
satisfies
with being but listening to about
spirituality and
gathering you know gems of phrases and
terms and again i'm not accused we are
all prone to this
okay and so we have to thereby
note that we have to turn
and ask ourselves maybe doing meta
towards ourselves
doing inquiring mindfulness why am i not
practicing
what's the anxiety i'm not facing what
am i what am i perhaps afraid of
what is it i don't want to actually have
changed in me
do some you know maybe meditative
questing on this
do some matter towards the anxiety apply
the five factors of
mindfulness and then independently do
reflection i'm gonna teach you guys this
later
but journal about it don't ruminate
think in your head write down your
thoughts
leave them for a while come back reread
them correct them as if you they were
written by somebody else like interact
them
and then write some more go away come
back so
first person while you're writing and
then third person as if somebody else
had written it
and you're trying to get the solomon
effect journal about it
really really work on this because if
you can
if you can get right the
anxiety up and disclosed then it won't
be you know being conflated with the
attraction
and that won't be subverted into just
consuming
um ideas and persons
i hope that's helpful and i hope you
don't feel i was trespassing
on you i'm not trying in any way to be
insulting we are all prone to this i am
prone to this
right i know this i know this
and so this is what you i'm recommending
you need to do
all right everybody uh thank you for the
excellent questions today
thank you for joining i want to thank my
dear friend and techno major mar my
beloved son jason
always behind the scenes making
everything happen please subscribe to
this channel to be notified of the next
video
you'll also find on the channel uh my
awakening from the meaning crisis
lecture series or my voices with verbacy
discussion series
where many of these topics and related
topics are discussed and examined in
greater depth and in a wider framework
invite others who might benefit to join
this series
we're slowing down the pace so people
have a time to catch up
people can review can soak it in uh
there is
also a link in the description of this
video uh to the discord server to chat
with others
um brett pleasure of doubt is running
that
he's uh acting as a liaison
there's people meeting on the discord
service and following the meditations
and then
meeting up and you know doing it sort of
uh after sit
uh discussion a salon uh you know
dialogue and then also setting that
within the broader context
of i guess all of my work and what's
going on right now
um as uh as the culture i think is
trying to wake up in certain ways
um so i strongly recommend that you
check out the discord server
a reminder that we are doing this every
weekday morning at 9
30 eastern time um every alternative
monday
starting next monday um
which is uh uh uh uh
the 25th i think or something like that
but the monday that the next monday
we're going to encounter
um and we will we do a dharma day
and then every other monday that can
that will continue on
please remember that continuity of
practice
especially when it gets hard in your
life or in your practice
is more important than quantity and
please remember
because it's come up a lot sative
remember
there is no enemy worse than your own
mind and body
but there is no friend
no ally greater than your own mind and
body
take care everyone and i'll see you all
tomorrow
you